<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- 
Copyright 2004 The Apache Software Foundation
Licensed  under the  Apache License,  Version 2.0  (the "License");
you may not use  this file  except in  compliance with the License.
You may obtain a copy of the License at 

http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
distributed  under the  License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
WITHOUT  WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS  OF ANY KIND, either  express  or
implied.

See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="ddewolf.AT.apache.D0T.org">David H. DeWolf</author>
    <title>Pluto Project | Declaration of Intent</title>
  </properties>

<body>
  <section name="Statement of Intent">
    <p>
    The Pluto Portlet Container is the Reference Implementation of 
    the Java Portlet Specification. As such, Pluto offers 
    the development community a reference for interpretation of
    the specification, portlet developers a container with which 
    compliant portlets can be tested, and portal developers 
    a compliant container with which they can integrate. 
    </p>
    
    <p>
    The following document attempts to clarify the development 
    priorities of the Apache Pluto project.
    </p>
    
    <p>
    The primary concern of the pluto community is to
    ensure that the Pluto Container maintains compatibility with
    the most current Java Portlet Specification.  Enhancements 
    and bug fixes should be completed in a manner in which 
    compatibility is maintained.
    </p>
    
    <p>
    It is the responsibility of the pluto development team to 
    ensure that no ambiguity is introduced into the reference 
    implementation.  No enhancements should be implemented which
    introduce questions about the specification.
    </p>
    
    <p>
    It is desirable for Pluto to become a robust and easy to use
    portlet container.  This will facilitate its wider acceptance
    and usage in the community.  In order to accomplish these goals,
    it is assumed that enhancements which are above and beyond the
    specification will be introduced.  These enhancements may be
    integrated with Pluto as long as they do not compromise the 
    integrity of the reference implementation as described above.
    </p>
    
    <p>
    Furthermore, functionality which is clearly beyond the scope
    of the specification should be documented as such and placed
    into a package which helps to distinguish it as such.  The Pluto
    container should always remain fully specification compliant
    and in working state when these enhancements are removed. In
    most cases, this removal should be supported through 
    configuration parameters.
    </p>
    
    <p>
    Finally, while the pluto project contains several subprojects, 
    it is important to realize that the container itself is the 
    most important aspect of the project.  It, in an of itself, is
    the Java Portlet reference implementation. The portalDriver
    (Pluto Test Portal), testsuite, and deployer exist to simplfy 
    the use and testing of the container. As such, any significant 
    enhancements to these components (most especially the portal 
    driver) should be scrutinized before implementation, as most 
    likely, it is outside the scope of the pluto project and belong 
    in a portal full implementation.
    </p>
      </section>
</body>
</document>

